Osip Mandelʹshtam Papers, 1900s-1970s (bulk 1914-1937 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- "Albums" no. 2, 3, and 4: copies of OM's poems to be given to someone to keep until later retrieval, undated; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  "Al'bom no. 2" ("Vtoroi Voronezh"): copies made in OM's lifetime, Voronezh, 1935-1937 all undated (1935-1937) (1937 March 9-April 7). "Al'bom no. 3": copies made by NM shortly after OM's death, 1938-1939 poems listed roughly in order they were written, for published poems only title and place of publication are given; unpublished poems copied in full (titles below), some apparently recorded from memory (inaccuracies, notes on forgotten lines) (1938-1939)
  1. Iz-za domov, iz-za lesov..., no. 322 -- 2. Kogda zaulybaetsia ditia..., no. 342 -- 3. Nynche den' kakoi-to zheltorotyi..., no. 329 -- 4. Moi shchegol, ia golovu zakinu..., no. 324 -- 5. Kogda shchegol v vozdushnoi sdobe..., no. 327 -- 6. Ia v serdtse veka -- put' neiasen..., no. 332 -- 7. Vnutri gory bezdeistvuet kumir..., no. 330 -- 8. Ne u tebia, ne u menia -- u nikh..., no. 328 -- 9. Sosnovoi roshchitsy zakon..., no. 335 -- 10. Plastinkoi tonen'koi zhilleta..., no. 334 -- 11. A master pushechnogo tsekha..., no. 333 -- 12. Nebo vecheri v stenu vliubilos'..., no. 377 -- 13. Dlinnoi zhazhdy dolzhnik vinovatyi..., no. 383 -- 14. Na menia natselilas' grusha i cheremukha..., no. 359 -- 15. Fleity grecheskoi teta i iota..., no. 387 -- 16. Chto delat' nam s ubitost'iu ravnin..., no. 350 -- 17. Drozhzhi mira dorogie..., no. 347 -- 18. Vlez besenok v mokroi sherstke..., no. 348 -- 19. Kak zemliu gde-nibud' nebesnyi kamen' budit..., no. 357 -- 20. Ne sravnivai: zhivushchii nesravnim..., no. 384 -- 21. Liubliu moroznoe dykhan'e..., no. 359 -- 22. Slyshu, slyshu rannii led..., no. 358 -- 23. Kuda mne detsia v etom ianvare?..., no. 360 -- 24. Gde sviazannyi i prigvozhdennyi ston?..., no. 356 -- 25. Kak derevo i med' -- Favorskogo polet..., no. 369 -- 26. Ia nynche v pautine svetovoi..., no. 355 -- 27. Eshche on pomnit bashmakov iznos..., no. 363 -- 28. Sredi narodnogo shuma i spekha..., no. 361 -- 29. Poiu, kogda gortan' syra, dusha sukha..., no. 365 -- 30. Kak svetoteni muchennik Rembrandt..., no. 369 -- 31. Vooruzhennyi zren'em uzkikh os..., no. 346 -- 32. Byli ochi ostree tochimoi kosy..., no. 368 -- 33. Razryvy kruglykh bukht, i khriashch i sineva..., no. 366 -- 34. Ia v l'vinyi rev i v krepost' pogruzhen..., no. 370 -- 35. Na doske malinovoi, chervonnoi..., no. 375 -- 36. Esli b menia nashi vragi vziali..., no. 372 -- 37. Ia videl ozero, stoiashchee otvesno..., no. 374 -- 38. Ia proshu, kak zhalosti i milosti..., no. 373 -- 39. Stikhi o neizvestnom soldate ( Etot vozdukh pust' budet svidetelem...), no. 362 -- 40. Gde liagushki fontanov, raskvakavshis'..., ( Rim), no. 381 -- 41. Zabludilsia ia v nebe. Chto delat'?..., no. 379 -- 42. Zabludilsia ia v nebe. Chto delat'?..., no. 378 -- 43. Ia skazhu eto nacherno, shopotom..., no. 376 -- 44. Nebo vecheri v tenu vliubilos'..., no. 377 -- 45. Mozhet byt', eto tochka bezumiia..., no. 380 -- 46. Kak po ulitsam Kieva-Viia..., 395 -- 47. Dlinnoi zhazhdy dolzhnik vinovatyi..., no. 383 -- 48. Fleity grecheskoi miata i iota..., no. 387 -- 49. Goncharami velik ostrov sinii..., no. 385 -- 50. Kuda kak strashno nam s toboi..., no. 202, Tiflis (1930) -- 51. Kak byk shestikrylyi i groznyi..., no. ?, Tiflis (1930) -- 52. Kak liub mne natugoi zhivushchii..., 217, Tiflis (1930) -- 53. Ne govori nikomu..., no. 201, Tiflis (1930) -- 54. I po zverinomu voet liud'e..., no. 220,Tiflis (1930) -- 55. Na politseiskoi bumage verzhe..., no. 189, Tiflis (1930) -- 56. Koliuchaia rech araratskoi doliny..., no. 216, Tiflis (1930) -- 57. My s toboi na kukhne posidim..., no. 224, Leningrad (1931) -- 58. Ia skazhu tebe s poslednei priamotoi..., no. 226 Moscow, Zoological Museum (1931) -- 59. Posle polunochi serdtse voruet..., no. 195, Moscow (1931) -- 60. Za gremuchuiu doblest' griadushchikh vekov...,no. 197, Moscow (1931) -- 61. Nepravda ( Ia s dymiashchei luchinoi vkhozhu...), no. 231, Moscow (1931) -- 62. Net, ne spriatat'sia mne ot velikoi mury..., no. 202, Moscow (1931) -- 63. Noch na dvore. Barskaia lzha..., no. 230, Moscow (1931) -- 64. Sokhrani moiu rech navsegda za privkus neschast'ia i dyma..., no. 235, Moscow (1931) -- 65. Ia p'iu za voennye astry, za vse, chem korili menia..., no. 233, Moscow (1931) -- 66. Zhil Aleksandr Gertsevich..., no. 228, Moscow (1931) -- 67. Kak narodnaia gromada..., no. 249, Moscow (1931) -- 68. Na vysokom perevale..., no. 248, Moscow (1931) -- 69. Kantsonna... ( Neuzheli ia uvizhu zavtra...), no. 236, Moscow (1931) -- 70-72. "Otryvki" (1931 July) -- 70. V god tridtsat' pervyi ot nachala veka..., no. 237 (undated) -- 71. Zakhochesh zhit', togda gliadish s ulybkoi..., no. 239 (undated) -- 72. Ia bol'she ne rebenok..., no. 240 (undated) -- 73. Segodnia mozhno sniat' dekal'komani..., no. 265, Moscow (1931) -- 74. Eshche daleko mne do patriarkha..., no. 251, Moscow (1931-1932) -- 75. O, kak my liubim litsemerit'..., no. 253, Moscow (1932) -- 76. Khudozhnik nam izobrazil..., no. 258, Moscow (1932) -- 77. Kogda v dalekuiu Koreiu..., no. 255, Moscow (1932) -- 78-80. Stikhi o russkoi poezii, Moscow (1932-1933) -- 78. Siad', Derzhavin, razvalis'..., no. 262 (undated) -- 79. Zashumela, zadrozhala..., no. 263 (undated) -- 80. Poliubil ia les prekrasnyi..., no. 264 (undated) -- 81. Vy slyshali, kak beguny ..., no. 229 (1933) -- 82. Uvy, ottaiala svecha...: last four stanzas of no. 256 ( Novellino), Moscow (1933) -- 83. Daite Tiutchevu strekozu..., no. 259, Moscow (1933) -- 84. Ne iskushai chuzhikh narechii, no postaraisia ikh zabyt'..., no. 240, Crimea (1933) -- 85. Drug Ariosta, drug Petrarki, Tasso drug..., 269, Crimea (1933) -- 86. Kvartira tikha, kak bumaga..., no. 272 (1933) -- 87-92. Vos'mistishia (1933) -- 87. Liubliu poiavlenie tkani..., no. 275, Moscow (1933) -- 88. Liubliu poiavlenie tkani..., no. 276 (undated) -- 89. Kogda, unichtozhiv nabrosok..., no. 250 (undated) -- 90. I klena zubchataia lapa..., no. 282 (undated) -- 91. V igol'chatykh chumnykh bokalakh..., no. 254 (undated) -- 92. I Shubert na vode, i Motsart v ptich'em game..., no. 281 (undated) -- 93. O babochka, o musul'manka..., no. 277 (undated) -- 94. Skazhi mne, chertezhnik pustyni..., no. 283 (undated) -- 95. Shestogo chuvstva kroshechnyi pridatok..., no. 248 (1932) -- 96. Preodolev zatverzhennost' prirody..., no. 279 (1934) -- 97. I ia vykhozhu iz prostranstva..., no. 285, Moscow (1933 Fall) -- 98. Kak solovei sirotstvuiushchii slavit..., no. 487 (1933) -- 99. Kogda usnet zemlia i zhar otpyshet..., no. 489 (1933) -- 100. Rechka, razbukhshaia ot slez solenykh..., no. 488 (1933) -- 101. Promchalis' dni moi, kak by olenei..., no. 490 (1933) -- 102. Golubye glaza i goriashchego cherepa kost'..., no. 288, Moscow (1934) -- 103. Ianvar' 1934 ( Menia presleduiut dve-tri sluchainykh frazy...), no. 289 (1934) -- 104. Kogda dushe i toropkoi i robkoi..., no. 291 (1934) -- 105. On dirizhiroval kavkazskimi gorami..., no. 293 (1934) -- 106-178. "Voronezhskie stikhi" (Voronezh poems) (1926-1937) -- 106. Chernozem (Pereuvazhena, perecherna, vsia v khole...), no. 299 (1935 April) -- 107. Pusti menia, otdai menia, Voronezh.. (1935) -- 108. Naushnichki, naushniki moi..., no. 300 (1935) -- 109. Ia zhivu na vazhnykh ogorodakh..., no. 304 (1935) -- 110. Kak na Kame-reke glazu temno kogda..., no. 308, with variant of last four lines (1935) -- 111. Ia smotrel, otdaliaias' na khvoinyi vostok..., no. 310 (1935) -- 112. Eshche my zhizn'iu polny v polnoi mere..., no. 302 (1935) -- 113. Stansy, no. 312: "Ia ne khochu sred' iunoshei teplichnykh...", "Liubliu shinel' krasnoarmeiskoi skladki": stanza 2 of no. 312 (1) "Prokliatyi shov, bezumnaia zateia...", "Podumaesh, kak v Cherdyne-golube...", "I ty, Moskva, sestra moia, legka...", "Ia dolzhen zhit', dysha i bol'sheveia...", "I ne ograblen ia i ne nadlomlen..." (1935) -- 114. Den' stoial o piati golovakh..., no. 313 (1935) -- 115. Ne muchnistoi babochkoiu beloi..., no. 320 (1935) -- 116. Bezhit volna, volnoi volne khrebet lomaia..., no. 319 (1935) -- 117. Ispolniu dymchatyi obriad..., no. 318 (1935) -- 118. Vozmozhna li zhenshchine mertvoi khvala?..., no. 314 (1935) -- 119. Rimskikh nochei polnovesnye slitki..., no. 284 (1935) -- 120. Skripachka ( Za Paganini dlinnopalym...), no. 298 (1935) -- 121. Iz-za domov, iz-za lesov..., no. 359 (1926) -- 122. Kogda zaulybaetsia ditia..., first two stanzas of no. 342 (1937) -- 123. Moi shchegol, ia golovu zakinu..., no. 324 (1926) -- 124. Kogda shchegol v vozdushnoi sdobe..., no. 327 (1926) -- 125. Nynche den' kakoi-to zheltorotyi..., no. 294 (1926) -- 126. Ne u menia, ne u tebia -- u nikh..., no. 328 (1926) -- 127. Vnutri gory bezdeistvuet kumir..., no. 330 (1926) -- 128. Ia v serdtse veka, put' neiasen..., no. 332 (1926) -- 129. Sosnovoi roshchitsy zakon..., no. 335 (1926) -- 130. Plastinkoi tonen'koi zhilleta..., no. 334 (1926) -- 131. Eta oblast' v temnovod'e..., no. 338 (1926) -- 132. Vekhi dal'nego oboza..., no. 340 (1926) -- 133. Kak podarok zapozdalyi..., no. 336 (1926) -- 134. Ottogo vse neudachi..., no. 337 (1926) -- 135. Ulybnis', iagnenok gnevnyi, s rafaeleva kholsta..., no. 321 (1926) -- 136. Tvoi zrachek v nebesnoi korke..., no. 345 (1937) -- 137. Kogda v vetviakh ponurykh..., no. 344 (1937). 138. Ia okolo Kol'tsova..., no. 343 (1937). 139. Chto delat' nam s ubitost'iu ravnin..., no. 350 (1937) -- 140. O, etot medlennyi odyshlivyi prostor..., no. 313 (1937) -- 141. V litso morozu ia gliazhu odin..., no. 349 (1937) -- 142. Drozhzhi mira dorogie..., no. 347 (1937) -- 143. Vlez besenok v mokroi sherstke..., no. 348 (1937) -- 144. Ne sravnivai: zhivushchii nesravnim..., no. 317 (1937) -- 145. Kak zemliu gde-nibud' nebesnyi kamen' budit..., no. 357 (1937) -- 146. Slyshu, slyshu rannii led..., no. 358 (1937) -- 147. Liubliu moroznoe dykhan'e..., no. 359 (1937) -- 148. Kuda mne det'sia v etom ianvare?..., no. 360 (1937) -- 149. Kak derevo i med' Favorskogo polet..., no. 369 (1937) -- 150. Gde sviazannyi i prigvozhdennyi ston?..., no. 356 (1937) -- 151. Ia nynche v pautine svetovoi..., no. 355 (1937) -- 152. Eshche on pomnit bashmakov iznos..., no. 363 (1937) -- 153. Sred' narodnogo shuma i spekha..., no. 361 (1937) -- 154. Razryvy kruglykh bukht, i khriashch, i sineva..., no. 366 (1937) -- 155. Vooruzhennyi zren'em uzkikh os..., no. 346 (1937) -- 156. Kak svetoteni muchennik Rembrandt..., no. 369 (1937) -- 157. Byli ochi, ostree tochimoi kosy..., no. 368 (1937) -- 158. Poiu, kogda gortan' syra, dusha sukha..., no. 327 (1937) -- 159. Eshche ne umer ty, eshche ty ne odin..., no. 354 (1937) -- 160. Ia v l'vinyi rov i v krepost' pogruzhen...,no. 370 (1937) -- 161. Na doske malinovoi, chervonnoi..., no. 375 (1937) -- 162. Ia videl ozero, stoiavshee otvesno..., no. 379 (1937) -- 163. Ia proshu, kak zhalosti i milosti..., no. 373 (1937) -- 164. Gde liagushki fontanov, raskvakavshis'..., no. 381 (1937) -- 165. Stikhi o neizvestnom soldate ( Etot vozdukh pust' budet svidetelem...), no. 362 (1937) -- 166. Esli b menia nashi vragi vziali..., no. 372 (1937) -- 167. Zabludilsia ia v nebe -- Chto delat'?..., no. 378 (1937) -- 168. Zabludilsia ia v nebe. Chto delat'?..., no. 379 (1937) -- 169. Ia skazhu eto nacherno, shopotom..., no. 376 (1937) -- 170. Ukrashalsia otbornoi sobachinoi..., no. 353 (1937) -- 171. Mozhet byt', eto tochka bezumiia..., no. 380 (1937) -- 172. O kak zhe ia khochu..., no. 384 (1937) -- 173. Kak po ulitsam Kieva-Viia..., 395 (1937) -- 174. Fleity grecheskoi teta i iota..., no. 387 (1937) -- 175. Dlinnoi zhazhdy dolzhnik vinovatyi..., no. 383 (1937) -- 176. Goncharami velik ostrov sinii..., no. 385 (1937) -- 177. Na menia natselilis' grusha da cheremukha..., no. 359: poem restored by memory, many inaccuracies and omissions, later crossed out in pencil (1937) -- 178. Ia k gubam podnushu etu zelen'..., no. 388 (1937). "Al'bom no. 4": copies of 1935-1937 (Voronezh) poems made by NM after OM's death, probably, 1939 (I. Semenko's estimate); most poems copied from memory, for some only title is given and blank page left (not listed below), others copied in full; many inaccuracies (1939) -- 179. Chernozem ( Pereuvazhena, perecherna, vsia v khole...), no. 299 (1935 April) -- 180. Ia zhivu na vazhnykh ogorodakh..., no. 304 (1935 April) -- 181. Ia dolzhen zhit', khotia ia dvazhdy umer..., no. 305 (1935 April) -- 182. Naushnichki, naushniki moi..., no. 300 (1935 April) -- 183. Pusti menia, otdai menia Voronezh..., no. 301 (1935 April) -- 184. Lishiv menia morei, razbega i razgona..., no. 307 (1935 April) -- 185. Eshche my zhizn'iu polny v vysshei mere..., no. 302 (1935 May) -- 186. Kak na Kame-reke
- "Albums" no. 5 and 6: copies of OM's poems made to be kept by someone until later retrieval (1926 October-1937 April), undated; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  "Al'bom no. 5": copies of poems made by NM in late 1930s from memory: 1. Kuda kak strashno nam s toboi..., no. 202, Tiflis2. Ty rozu Gafiza kolyshesh..., no. 2043. Akh, nichego ia ne vizhu..., no. 2964. Kak na Kame-reke glazu temno, kogda... no. 3085. Den' stoial o piati golovakh..., no. 3136. Ty krasok sebe pozhelala..., no. 2057. Zakutav rot, kak vlazhnuiu rozu..., no. 2078. Kogda v vetviakh ponurykh..., no. 3449. Drozhzhi mira dorogie..., no. 34710. Chto delat' nam s ubitost'iu ravnin?..., no. 35011. Kogda dushe i toropkoi i robkoi..., no. 29112. Eshche ne umer ty, eshche ty ne odin..., no. 35413. Byli ochi, ostree tochimoi kosy..., no. 36814. Lazur', da glina, glina da lazur'..., no. 21515. Ia tebia nikogda ne uvizhu..., no. 184, Tiflis16. Na politseiskoi bumage verzhe..., no. 21917. Ne govori nikomu..., no. 201, Tiflis18. Koliuchaia rech araratskoi doliny..., no. 21619. Kakoi-to grazhdanin..., no. 54420. Eshche daleko mne do patriarkha..., no. 25121. Ia k vorob'iam poidu i k reporteram..., no. 22322. Ruku platkom obmotai i v ventsenosnyi shipovnik..., no. 20823. Orushchikh kamnei gosudarstvo..., no.17924. Ne razvaliny -- net..., no. 18025. Liubliu moroznoe dykhan'e..., no. 35926. Kholodno roze v snegu..., 21127. Kakaia roskosh v nishchenskom selen'i..., no. 18328. O porfirnye tsokaia granity..., no. 21229. Otkuda privezli? Kogo? Kotoryi umer?..., no. 26330. Tvoi zrachek v nebesnoi korke..., no. 34531. A master pushechnogo tsekha..., no. 29932. Kak podarok zapozdalyi..., no. 33633. Slyshu, slyshu rannii led..., no. 35834. Ne iskushai chuzhikh narechii, no postaraisia ikh zabyt'..., no. 24035. Zabludilsia ia v nebe -- chto delat'?..., no. 37836. Kak po ulitsam Kieva-Viia..., 39537. Kogda unichtozhiv nabrosok..., no. 25038. I Shubert na vode, i Motsart v ptich'em game..., no. 28139. Kak narodnaia gromada..., no. 24940. Ia k gubam podnoshu etu zelen'..., no. 38841. Pusti menia, otdai menia, Voronezh.. 42. Ne muchnistoi babochkoiu beloi..., no. 32043. Segodnia mozhno sniat' dekal'komani..., no. 22144. Kak liub mne natugoi zhivushchii..., no. 217, Tiflis45. Dikaia koshka--armianskaia rech..., no. 247"Al'bom no. 6": copies of poems made by NM after OM's death (late 1930s) from memory: 46. Kuda kak strashno nam s toboi..., no. 20247. "Kak byk shestikrylyi i groznyi...": epigraph to Armenia cycle48. Kak liub mne natugoi zhivushchii..., 21749. Koliuchaia rech araratskoi doliny..., no. 18650. I po zverinomu voet liud'io..., no. 22051. Dikaia koshka -- armianskaia rech..., no. 24752. Na politseiskoi bumage verzhe..., no. 219, Tiflis53. Ne govori nikomu..., no. 201, Tiflis54. My s toboi na kukhne posidim..., no. 224, Leningrad55. Posle polunochi serdtse voruet..., no. 195, Moscow56. Ia skazhu tebe s poslednei priamotoi..., no. 226, Moscow57. Za gremuchuiu doblest' griadushchikh vekov..., no. 197, Moscow58. Ia s dymiashchei luchinoi vkhozhu..., no. 23159. Net, ne spriatatsia mne ot velikoi mury..., no. 20260. Koliut resnitsy, v grudi prikipela sleza ..., no. 22961. Noch na dvore. Barskaia lzha..., no. 230, Moscow62. Sokhrani moiu rech navsegda..., no. 23563. Ia p'iu za voennye astry, za vse, chem korili menia..., no. 23364. Zhil Aleksandr Gertsovich..., no. 22865. Eshche daleko mne do patriarkha..., no. 25166. Kak narodnaia gromada..., no. 24967. Kantsonna ( Neuzheli ia uvizhu zavtra...), no. 23668. Faetonshchik ( Na vysokom perevale...), no. 24869-70. Stikhi o russkoi poezii 71. Siad', Derzhavin, razvalis'..., no. 26272. Zashumela, zadrozhala..., no. 26373. Segodnia mozhno sniat' dekal'komani..., no. 22174. I po zverinomu voet liud'e..., no. 220, Tiflis75. Ia vernulsia v moi gorod, znakomyi do slez..., no. 221, Leningrad76. Lishiv menia morei, razbega i razleta..., no. 30777. Ulybnis', iagnenok gnevnyi s rafaeleva kholsta..., no. 321: first two stanzas78. S mirom derzhavnym ia byl lish rebiacheski sviazan..., no. 22279. My s toboi na kukhne posidim..., no. 224, Leningrad, date incorrect80. Posle polunochi serdtse voruet..., no. 195, Moscow81. Tam, gde krai byl dik..., no. 45382. Noch na dvore. Barskaia lzha..., no. 23083. Net, ne spriatatsia mne ot velikoi chumy..., no. 20284. Nepravda ( Ia s dymiashchei luchinoi vkhozhu...), no. 23185. O babochka, o musul'manka..., no. 27786. Ia p'iu za voennye astry, za vse chem korili menia..., no. 233, Moscow87. Roial' ( Kak parlament, zhuiushchii frondu...), no. 23488. Sokhrani moiu rech navsegda..., no. 235, Moscow89. Kantsonna ( Neuzheli ia uvizhu zavtra...), no. 23690. Poliubil ia les prekrasnyi..., no. 26491. Ia skazhu tebe s poslednei priamotoi..., no. 226, Moscow92. Za gremuchiu doblest' griadushchikh vekov..., no. 19793. Koliut resnitsy. V grudi prikipela sleza..., no. 22994. Zhil Aleksandr Gertsovich..., no. 22895. Polnoch v Moskve. Roskoshno buddiiskoe leto..., no. 26096-99. "Otryvki iz unichtozhennykh stikhov" (fragments of destroyed poems), 96. V god tridtsat' pervyi ot rozhden'ia veka..., no. 23797. Uzh ia liubliu moskovskie zakony..., no. 23898. Zakhochesh zhit', togda gliadish s ulybkoi..., no. 23999. Ia bol'she ne rebenok..., no. 240100. Faetonshchik ( Na vysokom perevale...), no. 248101. Bezhit volna volnoi volne khrebet lomaia..., no. 319102. "Tsvet vozdushnogo razboia i peshchernoi pustoty...," last two stanzas of no. 321 ( Ulybnis' iagnenok gnevnyi s rafaeleva kholsta...)
- "Al'bom Erenburga" (no. 7), undated; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  Typewritten copies of OM's poems, made in 1940s; belonged to I. Ehrenburg; notes and corrections in hand of NM (1915-1932 August)
  1-12. Armeniia: epigraph to cycle in hand of NM: 1. Ty rozu Gafiza kolyshesh..., no. 2042. Ty krasok sebe pozhelala..., no. 2052. Akh, nichego ia ne vizhu..., no. 2964. Zakutav rot, kak vlazhnuiu rozu..., no. 2075. Ruku platkom obmotai i v ventsenosnyi shipovnik..., no. 2086. Orushchikh kamnei gosudarstvo..., no. 2097. Ne razvaliny -- net!..., no. 1808. Kholodno roze v snegu..., 2119. O porfirnye tsokaia granity..., no. 21210. Kakaia roskosh v nishchenskom selen'i..., no. 18311. Ia tebia nikogda ne uvizhu..., no. 18412. Lazur', da glina! Glina, da lazur'!..., no. 215, Tiflis, date in hand of NM, probably refers to whole cycle -- 13. Dovol'no kuksit'sia, bumagi v stol zasunem..., no. 247 -- 14. O, kak my liubim litsemerit'..., no. 253 -- 15. Kak parlament, zhuiushchii frondu..., no. 234, date and note on publication in hand of NM -- 16. Lamark ( Byl starik, zastenchivyi, kak mal'chik...), no. 254 -- 17. Batiushkov ( Slovno guliaka s volshebnoiu trost'iu), no. 261 -- 18. Tam, gde kupalni, bumagopriadil'ni..., no. 224 -- 19. Leningrad ( Ia vernulsia v moi gorod, znakomyi do slez...), no. 221 -- 20. Polnoch v Moskve ( Polnoch v Moskve. Roskoshno buddiiskoe leto...), no. 208 -- 21. K nemetskoi rechi ( Sebia gubia, sebe protivorecha...), 266 -- 22. S mirom derzhavnym ia byl lish rebiacheski sviazan..., no. 222, date corrected in hand of NM -- 23. Voina. Opiat' raznogolositsa..., variant of first three stanzas of no. 197 ( A nebo budushchim beremenno...) -- 24. Davaite slushat' groma propoved'..., first published variant of 5 stanzas later divided in two poems: no. 197 ( Opiat' voiny raznogolositsa...) and no. 139 ( Kak tel'tse malen'koe krylyshkom...); published in collection Let, pp.25-26 -- 25. Synov'ia Aimona ( Prishli chetyre brata...), no. 461, pencil corrections, insertions and date in hand of NM -- 26. Encyclica ( Est' obitaemaia dukhom...), no. 71 -- 27. Meganon ( Eshche daleko asfodelei...), no. 93 -- 28. Akter i rabochii ( Zdes', na tverdoi ploshchadke iakht-kluba...), no. 195 -- 29. Ia p'iu za voennye astry, za vse, chem korili menia..., no. 233, Moscow: date in hand of NM -- 30. Faetonshchik ( Na vysokom perevale...), no. 248 -- 31. Nepravda ( Ia s dymiashchei luchinoi vkhozhu...), no. 231, date in hand of NM -- 32. Lazur' da glina, glina da lazur'..., no. 215 -- 33. Posle polunochi serdtse voruet..., no. 195, Moscow -- 34. Zhil Aleksandr Gertsovich..., no. 228 -- 35. Daite Tiutchevu strekozu..., no. 259: 2 variants -- 36. Impressionizm ( Khudozhnik nam izobrazil...), no. 258 -- 37. Novellino ( Vy pomnite, kak beguny...), no. 256 -- 38. Za gremuchuiu doblest' griadushchikh vekov..., no. 197, date in hand of NM
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. "Sevan": draft manuscripts and notes, 3 envelopes with collated items (1931), undated; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  1. drafts in hand of OM, hardcover notebook -- 2. drafts in hand of OM and NM, research notes on Armenian language and mythology, bibliographical notes in OM's hand -- 3. 1 sheet of transcript of Armenian legend, in OM's hand
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. "Sukhum": draft manuscripts, transcripts of drafts; 2 envelopes with collated items (1931), undated; 1 folder (Folder 23)
  1. drafts in OM's hand, one in NM's hand, each fragment in individual envelope with full transcript on cover in hand of D. Borisov, two last fragments untranscribed -- 2. drafts in OM's hand; for D. Borisov's transcript of p. 4, see Box 2, Folder 20
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. "Frantsuzy": draft manuscripts; 3 envelopes with collated items (1931), undated; 1 folder (Folder 24)
  1. drafts in OM's hand -- 2. drafts in OM's hand -- 3. ["Zametki ob impressionistakh"(?)]: two loose fragments not included in final version of Puteshestvie v Armeniiu, title on cover of envelope in hand of I. Semenko; could be part of material for essay "Frantsuzy"
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu: draft manuscripts, transcripts of drafts; 3 envelopes with collated items (1931-1932), undated; 1 folder (Folder 25)
  1. "Vokrug naturalistov": 1 sheet in OM's hand; 1 notebook of research notes, list of Linneus's apes -- 2. ["Pallas"]: draft fragments in OM's hand; article not included in final version of Puteshestvie v Armeniiu; 12 small envelopes containing collated fragments -- 3. ["Pallas"]: draft fragments in OM's hand, uncollated, for D. Borisov's transcript of last three sheets see Box 2, Folder 20
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. "Ashtarak", 1931-1932; 1 folder (Folder 26)
  12 draft fragments in OM's hand, collated according to published text, most fragments transcribed on envelope covers by D. Borisov
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. "Alagez", 1931-1932; 1 folder (Folder 27)
  21 collated fragments of manuscript; fragments 1-18 in author's hand (2-17 with transcripts on envelope covers by D. Borisov), fragments 19-21 in hand of NM
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. Addition to essay "Vokrug naturalistov," published as ["Literaturnyi stil' Darvina"], 1931-1932; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  :Typewritten transcript of author's notebook (original lost), for other fragments of same draft see Box 5, Fol. 8
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu: original typescript of final version, parts missing, 1930s; 1 folder (Folder 2)
- Letter from OM to Marietta Shaginian: fragment of draft, circa 1932; 1 folder (Folder 3)
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. "Vokrug naturalistov": 6 copies of final version manuscript (1932), undated; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  1-5. 5 typescripts of final version (as submitted for publication?); 3-5 identical, 1 and 2 slightly different (most complete -- I. Semenko) -- 6. copy of final version in hand of NM (incomplete)